[MUSIC PLAYING]
TOM CRUISE: I'm going
to show you some magic.
It's the real thing.
[LAUGHTER]
I mean, it's all the real thing.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, Harvard
University's Introduction
to the Intellectual
Enterprises of Computer Science
and the Art of Programming.
My name is David Malan, and this
is our family-friendly introduction
to artificial intelligence or AI, which
seems to be everywhere these days.
But first, a word on these
rubber ducks, which your students
might have had for some time.
Within the world of computer science,
and programming in particular,
there's this notion of rubber
duck debugging or rubber ducking--
--whereby in the absence of a colleague,
a friend, a family member, a teaching
fellow who might be able to answer
your questions about your code,
especially when it's
not working, ideally you
might have at least a rubber
duck or really any inanimate
object on your desk with whom to talk.
And the idea is, that in expressing your
logic, talking through your problems,
even though the duck
doesn't actually respond,
invariably, you hear eventually
the illogic in your thoughts
and the proverbial light bulb goes off.
Now, for students online
for some time, CS50
has had a digital
version thereof, whereby
in the programming environment
that CS50 students use,
for the past several years, if they
don't have a rubber duck on their desk,
they can pull up this interface here.
And if they begin a
conversation like, I'm
hoping you can help me solve
some problem, up until recently,
CS50's virtual rubber duck
would simply quack once, twice,
or three times in total.
But we have anecdotal
evidence that alone
was enough to get students to realize
what it is they were doing wrong.
But of course, more recently has
this duck and so many other ducks,
so to speak, around the
world, come to life really.
And your students have been
using artificial intelligence
in some form within CS50 as
a virtual teaching assistant.
And what we'll do today,
is reveal not only
how we've been using and
leveraging AI within CS50,
but also how AI itself works, and to
prepare you better for the years ahead.
So last year around this time,
like DALL-E 2 and image generation
were all of the rage.
You might have played with this, whereby
you can type in some keywords and boom,
you have a dynamically generated image.
Similar tools are like Midjourney,
which gives you even more realistic 3D
imagery.
And within that world
of image generation,
there were nonetheless some tells,
like an observant viewer could tell
that this was probably generated by AI.
And in fact, a few months
ago, The New York Times
took a look at some of these tools.
And so, for instance, here
is a sequence of images
that at least at left, isn't
all that implausible that this
might be an actual photograph.
But in fact, all three of
these are AI-generated.
And for some time, there
was a certain tell.
Like AI up until recently, really
wasn't really good at the finer details,
like the fingers are not quite right.
And so you could have that sort of hint.
But I dare say, AI is getting
even better and better,
such that it's getting harder to
discern these kinds of things.
So if you haven't already, go
ahead and take out your phone
if you have one with you.
And if you'd like to partake,
scan this barcode here,
which will lead you to a URL.
And on your screen, you'll have an
opportunity in a moment to buzz in.
If my colleague, Rongxin, wouldn't
mind joining me up here on stage.
We'll ask you a sequence of
questions and see just how
prepared you are for
this coming world of AI.
So for instance, once
you've got this here,
code scanned, if you don't, that's fine.
You can play along at home or
alongside the person next to you.
Here are two images.
And my question for you is,
which of these two images, left
or right, was generated by AI?
Which of these two was
generated by AI, left or right?
And I think Rongxin, we
can flip over and see
as the responses start to come in.
So far, we're about 20% saying
left, 70 plus percent saying right.
3%, 4%, comfortably admitting
unsure, and that's fine.
Let's wait for a few more
responses to come in,
though I think the
right-hand folks have it.
And let's go ahead and flip back
and see what the solution is.
In this case, it was, in fact, the
right-hand side that was AI-generated.
So, that's great.
I'm not sure what it means
that we figured this one out,
but let's try one more here.
So let me propose that we
consider now these two images.
It's the same code.
So if you still have your phone
up, you don't need to scan again.
It's going to be the same URL here.
But just in case you closed it.
Let's take a look now
at these two images.
Which of these, left or
right, was AI-generated?
Left or right this time?
Rongxin, should we take a
look at how it's coming in?
Oh, it's a little closer this time.
Left or right?
Right's losing a little
ground, maybe as people
are changing their answers to left.
More people are unsure this time,
which is somewhat revealing.
Let's give folks another second or two.
And Rongxin, should we flip back?
The answer is, actually a trick
question, since they were both AI.
So most of you, most of
you were, in fact, right.
But if you take a glance at this,
is getting really, really good.
And so this is just a taste of the
images that we might see down the line.
And in fact, that video
with which we began,
Tom Cruise, as you might have
gleaned, was not, in fact, Tom Cruise.
That was an example of
a deepfake, a video that
was synthesized, whereby a different
human was acting out those motions,
saying those words, but software,
artificial intelligence-inspired
software was mutating the actual
image and faking this video.
So it's all fun and games for now as
we tinker with these kinds of examples,
but suffice it to say, as we've begun
to discuss in classes like this already,
disinformation is only going to become
more challenging in a world where
it's not just text, but it's imagery.
And all the more, soon video.
But for today, we'll focus
really on the fundamentals, what
it is that's enabling technologies like
these, and even more familiarly, text
generation, which is all the rage.
And in fact, it seems just a few months
ago, probably everyone in this room
started to hear about
tools like ChatGPT.
So we thought we'd do one
final exercise here as a group.
And this was another piece
in The New York Times
where they asked the audience,
"Did a fourth grader write this?
Or the new chatbot?"
So another opportunity to
assess your discerning skills.
So same URL.
So if you still have your phone
open and that same interface open,
you're in the right place.
And here, we'll take a final
stab at two essays of sorts.
Which of these essays was written by AI?
Essay 1 or Essay 2?
And as folks buzz in,
I'll read the first.
Essay 1.
I like to bring a yummy sandwich
and a cold juice box for lunch.
Sometimes I'll even pack a tasty piece
of fruit or a bag of crunchy chips.
As we eat, we chat and laugh and catch
up on each other's day, dot, dot, dot.
Essay 2.
My mother packs me a sandwich,
a drink, fruit, and a treat.
When I get in the lunchroom, I
find an empty table and sit there
and I eat my lunch.
My friends come and sit down with me.
Dot, dot, dot.
Rongxin, should we see what folks think?
It looks like most of you think
that Essay 1 was generated by AI.
And in fact, if we flip back to the
answer here, it was, in fact, Essay 1.
So it's great that we now already
have seemingly this discerning eye,
but let me perhaps
deflate that enthusiasm
by saying it's only going to get
harder to discern one from the other.
And we're really now on the bleeding
edge of what's soon to be possible.
But most everyone in this
room has probably by now
seen, tried, certainly heard of ChatGPT,
which is all about textual generation.
Within CS50 and within
academia more generally,
have we been thinking about, talking
about, how whether to use or not
use these kinds of technologies.
And if the students in the room haven't
told the family members in the room
already, this here is an excerpt
from CS50's own syllabus this year,
whereby we have deemed tools like
ChatGPT in their current form,
just too helpful.
Sort of like an overzealous
friend who in school,
who just wants to give you all of the
answers instead of leading you to them.
And so we simply prohibit by
policy using AI-based software,
such as ChatGPT, third-party tools like
GitHub Copilot, Bing Chat, and others
that suggests or completes answers
to questions or lines of code.
But it would seem reactionary to
take away what technology surely has
some potential upsides for education.
And so within CS50 this semester,
as well as this past summer,
have we allowed students to use
CS50's own AI-based software, which
are in effect, as we'll
discuss, built on top
of these third-party
tools, ChatGPT from OpenAI,
companies like Microsoft and beyond.
And in fact, what students can now
use, is this brought to life CS50 duck,
or DDB, Duck Debugger,
within a website of our own,
CS50 AI, and another that your
students know known as cs50.dev.
So students are using
it, but in a way where
we have tempered the enthusiasm
of what might otherwise
be an overly helpful
duck to model it more
akin to a good teacher,
a good teaching fellow,
who might guide you to the answers,
but not simply hand them outright.
So what does that actually mean, and
in what form does this duck come?
Well, architecturally, for those of
you with engineering backgrounds that
might be curious as to how
this is actually implemented,
if a student here in the class has
a question, virtually in this case,
they somehow ask these questions of
this central web application, cs50.ai.
But we, in turn, have
built much of our own logic
on top of third-party services, known
as APIs, application programming
interfaces, features that
other companies provide
that people like us can use.
So as they are doing really
a lot of the heavy lifting,
the so-called large
language models are there.
But we, too, have information
that is not in these models yet.
For instance, the words
that came out of my mouth
just last week when we had a lecture
on some other topic, not to mention all
of the past lectures and homework
assignments from this year.
So we have our own
vector database locally
via which we can search for
more recent information,
and then hand some of that information
into these models, which you might
recall, at least for OpenAI,
is cut off as of 2021 as
of now, to make the
information even more current.
So architecturally,
that's sort of the flow.
But for now, I thought I'd
share at a higher level what
it is your students are
already familiar with,
and what will soon be more broadly
available to our own students
online as well.
So what we focused on
is, what's generally
now known as prompt engineering,
which isn't really a technical phrase,
because it's not so much engineering
in the traditional sense.
It really is just English,
what we are largely
doing when it comes to
giving the AI the personality
of a good teacher or a good duck.
So what we're doing, is giving it what's
known as a system prompt nowadays,
whereby we write some English sentences,
send those English sentences to OpenAI
or Microsoft, that sort of
teaches it how to behave.
Not just using its own
knowledge out of the box,
but coercing it to behave a little
more educationally constructively.
And so for instance, a
representative snippet
of English that we
provide to these services
looks a little something like this.
Quote, unquote, "You are a friendly and
supportive teaching assistant for CS50.
You are also a rubber duck.
You answer student questions only about
CS50 and the field of computer science,
do not answer questions
about unrelated topics.
Do not provide full
answers to problem sets,
as this would violate academic honesty.
And so in essence, and you can
do this manually with ChatGPT,
you can tell it or ask it how to behave.
We, essentially, are
doing this automatically,
so that it doesn't just
hand answers out of the box
and knows a little
something more about us.
There's also in this world of AI
right now the notion of a user
prompt versus that system prompt.
And the user prompt, in our case, is
essentially the student's own question.
I have a question about x, or I have
a problem with my code here in y,
so we pass to those same
APIs, students' own questions
as part of this so-called user prompt.
Just so you're familiar now with
some of the vernacular of late.
Now, the programming
environment that students
have been using this whole
year is known as Visual Studio
Code, a popular open source,
free product, that most--
so many engineers around
the world now use.
But we've instrumented it to be
a little more course-specific
with some course-specific features that
make learning within this environment
all the easier.
It lives at cs50.dev.
And as students in this
room know, that as of now,
the virtual duck lives
within this environment
and can do things like explain
highlighted lines of code.
So here, for instance, is a screenshot
of this programming environment.
Here is some arcane looking code in
a language called C, that we've just
left behind us in the class.
And suppose that you don't understand
what one or more of these lines of code
do.
Students can now highlight those lines,
right-click or Control click on it,
select explain highlighted
code, and voila,
they see a ChatGPT-like explanation of
that very code within a second or so,
that no human has typed out, but
that's been dynamically generated
based on this code.
Other things that the duck
can now do for students
is advise students on how to improve
their code style, the aesthetics,
the formatting thereof.
And so for instance, here is
similar code in a language called C.
And I'll stipulate that it's very messy.
Everything is left-aligned
instead of nicely indented,
so it looks a little more structured.
Students can now click a button.
They'll see at the
right-hand side in green
how their code should ideally look.
And if they're not quite sure
what those changes are or why,
they can click on, explain changes.
And similarly, the duck
advises them on how and why
to turn their not great
code into greater code,
from left to right respectively.
More compellingly and more generalizable
beyond CS50 and beyond computer
science, is AI's ability to
answer most of the questions
that students might now ask online.
And we've been doing asynchronous Q&A
for years via various mobile or web
applications and the like.
But to date, it has been
humans, myself included,
responding to all of those questions.
Now the duck has an opportunity to chime
in, generally within three seconds,
because we've integrated
it into an online Q&A tool
that students in CS50 and elsewhere
across Harvard have long used.
So here's an anonymized screenshot
of a question from an actual student,
but written here as John
Harvard, who asked this summer,
in the summer version of
CS50, what is flask exactly?
So fairly definitional question.
And here is what the duck spit
out, thanks to that architecture
I described before.
I'll stipulate that this is
correct, but it is mostly
a definition, akin to what Google or
Bing could already give you last year.
But here's a more nuanced
question, for instance,
from another anonymized student.
In this question here, the
student's including an error message
that they're seeing.
They're asking about that.
And they're asking a little more
broadly and qualitatively, is there
a more efficient way to write this
code, a question that really is best
answered based on experience.
Here, I'll stipulate that the duck
responded with this answer, which
is actually pretty darn good.
Not only responding in English,
but with some sample starter code
that would make sense in this context.
And at the bottom it's worth noting,
because none of this technology
is perfect just yet, it's still
indeed very bleeding edge,
and so what we have chosen to do within
CS50 is include disclaimers, like this.
I am an experimental bot, quack.
Do not assume that my reply is
accurate unless you see that it's
been endorsed by humans, quack.
And in fact, at top right, the
mechanism we've been using in this tool
is usually within minutes.
A human, whether it's a teaching
fellow, a course assistant, or myself,
will click on a button like this
to signal to our human students
that yes, like the duck is spot on here,
or we have an opportunity, as always,
to chime in with our own responses.
Frankly, that disclaimer, that
button, will soon I do think
go away, as the software
gets better and better.
But for now, that's how
we're modulating exactly
what students' expectations
might be when it
comes to correctness or incorrectness.
It's common too in programming,
to see a lot of error messages,
certainly when you're
learning first-hand.
A lot of these error messages
are arcane, confusing,
certainly to students, versus
the people who wrote them.
Soon students will see a box like this.
Whenever one of their
terminal window programs errs,
they'll be assisted too with
English-like, TF-like support when
it comes to explaining what it is
that went wrong with that command.
And ultimately, what
this is really doing
for students in our
own experience already,
is providing them really with
virtual office hours and 24/7,
which is actually quite compelling
in a university environment,
where students' schedules
are already tightly packed,
be it with academics, their
curriculars, athletics, and the like--
--and they might have
enough time to dive
into a homework assignment, maybe eight
hours even, for something sizable.
But if they hit that wall
a couple of hours in, yeah,
they can go to office hours or they can
ask a question asynchronously online,
but it's really not optimal
in the moment support
that we can now provide
all the more effectively
we hope, through software, as well.
So if you're curious.
Even if you're not a technophile
yourself, anyone on the internet
can go to cs50.ai and experiment
with this user interface.
This one here actually resembles ChatGPT
itself, but it's specific to CS50.
And here again is just a
sequence of screenshots
that I'll stipulate
for today's purposes,
are pretty darn good in akin to what I
myself or a teaching fellow would reply
to and answer to a student's
question, in this case,
about their particular code.
And ultimately, it's
really aspirational.
The goal here ultimately is to really
approximate a one-to-one teacher
to student ratio, which despite all
of the resources we within CS50,
we within Harvard and
places like Yale have,
we certainly have never
had enough resources
to approximate what
might really be ideal,
which is more of an apprenticeship
model, a mentorship, whereby it's just
you and that teacher working one-to-one.
Now we still have humans, and the goal
is not to reduce that human support,
but to focus it all the more consciously
on the students who would benefit most
from some impersonal one-to-one
support versus students
who would happily take it at any hour
of the day more digitally via online.
And in fact, we're still in
the process of evaluating just
how well or not well all of this works.
But based on our summer experiment
alone with about 70 students
a few months back, one student
wrote us at term's end it--
--"felt like having a personal tutor.
I love how AI bots will answer questions
without ego and without judgment.
Generally entertaining even
the stupidest of questions
without treating them
like they're stupid.
It has an, as one could expect,"
ironically, "an inhuman level
of patience."
And so I thought that's telling
as to how even one student is
perceiving these new possibilities.
So let's consider now
more academically what
it is that's enabling those
kinds of tools, not just
within CS50, within computer science,
but really, the world more generally.
What the whole world's
been talking about
is generative artificial intelligence.
AI that can generate images,
generate text, and sort of
mimic the behavior of
what we think of as human.
So what does that really mean?
Well, let's start
really at the beginning.
Artificial intelligence is
actually a technique, a technology,
a subject that's actually
been with us for some time,
but it really was the introduction of
this very user-friendly interface known
as ChatGPT.
And some of the more recent academic
work over really just the past five
or six years, that really allowed
us to take a massive leap forward
it would seem technologically, as
to what these things can now do.
So what is artificial intelligence?
It's been with us for some time,
and it's honestly, so omnipresent,
that we take it for granted nowadays.
Gmail, Outlook, have gotten
really good at spam detection.
If you haven't checked your
spam folder in a while,
that's testament to
just how good they seem
to be at getting it out of your inbox.
Handwriting recognition has
been with us for some time.
I dare say, it, too, is only
getting better and better
the more the software is able to
adapt to different handwriting
styles, such as this.
Recommendation histories
and the like, whether you're
using Netflix or any
other service, have gotten
better and better at recommending
things you might like based on things
you have liked, and
maybe based on things
other people who like the same
thing as you might have liked.
And suffice it to say,
there's no one at Netflix
akin to the old VHS
stores of yesteryear,
who are recommending to you
specifically what movie you might like.
And there's no code, no algorithm that
says, if they like x, then recommend y,
else recommend z, because there's just
too many movies, too many people, too
many different tastes in the world.
So AI is increasingly sort of looking
for patterns that might not even
be obvious to us humans,
and dynamically figuring out
what might be good for me, for
you or you, or anyone else.
Siri, Google Assistant, Alexa, any
of these voice recognition tools
that are answering questions.
That, too, suffice it to
say, is all powered by AI.
But let's start with something a little
simpler than any of those applications.
And this is one of the first arcade
games from yesteryear known as Pong.
And it's sort of like table tennis.
And the person on the left can
move their paddle up and down.
Person on the right can do the same.
And the goal is to get the
ball past the other person,
or conversely, make sure it hits
your paddle and bounces back.
Well, somewhat simpler than this
insofar as it can be one player,
is another Atari game
from yesteryear known
as Breakout, whereby you're
essentially just trying
to bang the ball against the
bricks to get more and more points
and get rid of all of those bricks.
But all of us in this room
probably have a human instinct
for how to win this game, or
at least how to play this game.
For instance, if the ball
pictured here back in the '80s
as a single red dot just left the
paddle, pictured here as a red line,
where is the ball
presumably going to go next?
And in turn, which direction
should I slide my paddle?
To the left or to the right?
So presumably, to the left.
And we all have an eye for what seemed
to be the digital physics of that.
And indeed, that would then
be an algorithm, sort of step
by step instructions for
solving some problem.
So how can we now translate that human
intuition to what we describe more
as artificial intelligence?
Not nearly as sophisticated
as those other applications,
but we'll indeed,
start with some basics.
You might know from economics or
strategic thinking or computer science,
this idea of a decision tree
that allows you to decide,
should I go this way or this way
when it comes to making a decision.
So let's consider how we could draw
a picture to represent even something
simplistic like Breakout.
Well, if the ball is left of the paddle,
is a question or a Boolean expression
I might ask myself in code.
If yes, then I should move my paddle
left, as most everyone just said.
Else, if the ball is not left
of paddle, what do I want to do?
Well, I want to ask a question.
I don't want to just
instinctively go right.
I want to check, is the ball
to the right of the paddle,
and if yes, well, then yes, go
ahead and move the paddle right.
But there is a third
situation, which is--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Right.
Like, don't move, it's
coming right at you.
So that would be the
third scenario here.
No, it's not to the right or to the
left, so just don't move the paddle.
You got lucky, and it's coming,
for instance, straight down.
So Breakout is fairly straightforward
when it comes to an algorithm.
And we can actually translate this
as any CS50 student now could,
to code or pseudocode, sort of
English-like code that's independent
of Java, C, C++ and all of the
programming languages of today.
So in English pseudocode,
while a game is
ongoing, if the ball is left of
paddle, I should move paddle left.
Else if ball is right of the paddle,
it should say paddle, that's a bug,
not intended today, move paddle right.
Else, don't move the paddle.
So that, too, represents a
translation of this intuition to code
that's very deterministic.
You can anticipate all possible
scenarios captured in code.
And frankly, this should be the
most boring game of Breakout,
because the paddle should just
perfectly play this game, assuming
there's no variables or
randomness when it comes to speed
or angles or the like, which real
world games certainly try to introduce.
But let's consider another
game from yesteryear
that you might play with your kids
today or you did yourself growing up.
Here's tic-tac-toe.
And for those unfamiliar, the
goal is to get three O's in a row
or three X's in a row, vertically,
horizontally, or diagonally.
So suppose it's now X's turn.
If you've played
tic-tac-toe, most of you
probably just have an immediate instinct
as to where X should probably go,
so that it doesn't lose instantaneously.
But let's consider in the more general
case, how do you solve tic-tac-toe.
Frankly, if you're in the
habit of losing tic-tac-toe,
but you're not trying
to lose tic-tac-toe,
you're actually playing it wrong.
Like, you should minimally be able
to always force a tie in tic-tac-toe.
And better yet, you should be
able to beat the other person.
So hopefully, everyone now will
soon walk away with this strategy.
So how can we borrow inspiration
from those same decision trees
and do something similar here?
So if you, the player, ask yourself,
can I get three in a row on this turn?
Well, if yes, then you should do
that and play the X in that position.
Play in the square to
get three in a row.
Straight forward.
If you can't get three in a row in this
turn, you should ask another question.
Can my opponent get three
in a row in their next turn?
Because then you better preempt
that by moving into that position.
Play in the square to block
opponent's three in a row.
What if though, that's
not the case, right?
What if there aren't even that
many X's and O's on the board?
If you're in the habit
of just kind of playing
randomly, like you might not be
playing optimally as a good AI could.
So if no, it's kind of a question mark.
In fact, there's probably
more to this tree,
because we could think
through, what if I go there.
Wait a minute, what if I
go there or there or there?
You can start to think a few steps ahead
as a computer could do much better even
than us humans.
So suppose, for instance, it's O's turn.
Now those of you who are
very good at tic-tac-toe
might have an instinct for where to go.
But this is an even harder
problem, it would seem.
I could go in eight
possible places if I'm O.
But let's try to break that down
more algorithmically, as in AI would.
And let's recognize, too, that with
games in particular, one of the reasons
that AI was so early adopted in
these games, playing the CPU,
is that games really lend
themselves to defining them,
if taking the fun out
of it mathematically.
Defining them in terms of inputs
and outputs, maybe paddle moving
left or right, ball moving up or down.
You can really quantize it
at a very boring low level.
But that lends itself then
to solving it optimally.
And in fact, with most games,
the goal is to maximize or maybe
minimize some math function, right?
Most games, if you have scores,
the goal is to maximize your score,
and indeed, get a high score.
So games lend themselves to a
nice translation to mathematics,
and in turn here, AI solutions.
So one of the first algorithms one
might learn in a class on algorithms
and on artificial
intelligence is something
called minimax, which alludes
to this idea of trying
to minimize and/or maximize something
as your function, your goal.
And it actually derives its inspiration
from these same decision trees
that we've been talking about.
But first, a definition.
Here are three representative
tic-tac-toe boards.
Here is one in which O has
clearly won, per the green.
Here is one in which X has
And this one in the middle
just represents a draw.
Now, there's a bunch of other ways
that tic-tac-toe could end, but here's
just three representative ones.
But let's make tic-tac-toe
even more boring
than it might have always struck you as.
Let's propose that this
kind of configuration
should have a score of negative 1.
If O wins, it's a negative 1.
If X wins, it's a positive 1.
And if no one wins, we'll call it a 0.
We need some way of talking about and
reasoning about which of these outcomes
is better than the other.
And what's simpler than
0, 1 and negative 1?
So the goal though, of
X, it would seem, is
to maximize its score, but the
goal of O is to minimize its score.
So X is really trying to get positive
1, O is really trying to get negative 1.
And no one really wants 0, but that's
better than losing to the other person.
So we have now a way to define
what it means to win or lose.
Well, now we can employ a strategy here.
Here, just as a quick check, what
would the score be of this board?
Just so everyone's on the same page.
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: Or, so 1, because X has
one and we just stipulated arbitrarily,
this means that this
board has a value of 1.
Now let's put it into a
more interesting context.
Here, a game has been played
for a few moves already.
There's two spots left.
No one has won just yet.
And suppose that it's O's turn now.
Now, everyone probably has an
instinct already as to where to go,
but let's try to break this
down more algorithmically.
So what is the value of this board?
Well, we don't know yet,
because no one has won,
so let's consider what
could happen next.
So we can draw this actually
as a tree, as before.
Here, for instance, is
what might happen if O
goes into the top left-hand corner.
And here's what might happen if O goes
into the bottom middle spot instead.
We should ask ourselves, what's
the value of this board, what's
the value of this board?
Because if O's purpose in
life is to minimize its score,
it's going to go left or right based on
whichever yields the smallest number.
Negative 1, ideally.
But we're still not sure yet, because
we don't have definitions for boards
with holes in them like this.
So what could happen next here?
Well, it's obviously
going to be X's turn next.
So if X moves, unfortunately, X
has one in this configuration.
We can now conclude that the value
of this board is what number?
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: So 1.
And because there's only one way to
reach this board, by transitivity,
you might as well think of the value
of this previous board as also 1,
because no matter what, it's going
to lead to that same outcome.
And so the value of this board is
actually still to be determined,
because we don't know if O is
going to want to go with the 1,
and probably not, because
that means X wins.
But let's see what the
value of this board is.
Well, suppose that indeed, X goes
in that top left corner here.
What's the value of this board here?
0, because no one has won.
There's no X's or O's three in a row.
So the value of this board is 0.
There's only one way
logically to get there,
so we might as well think of the
value of this board as also 0.
And so now, what's the
value of this board?
Well, if we started the story
by thinking about O's turn,
O's purpose is the min in minimax,
then which move is O going to make?
Go to the left or go to the right?
O's was probably going
to go to the right
and make the move that leads to,
whoops, that leads to this board,
because even though O can't win in this
configuration, at least X didn't win.
So it's minimized its score relatively,
even though it's not a clean win.
Now, this is all fine and
good for a configuration
of the board that's like almost done.
There's only two moves left.
The game's about to end.
But if you kind of expand
in your mind's eye,
how did we get to this
branch of the decision tree,
if we rewind one step where
there's three possible moves,
frankly, the decision
tree is a lot bigger.
If we rewind further in your
mind's eye and have four moves
left or five moves or
all nine moves left,
imagine just zooming out, out, and out.
This is becoming a massive,
massive tree of decisions.
Now, even so, here is that same
subtree, the same decision tree
we just looked at.
This is the exact same thing,
but I shrunk the font so
that it appears here on the screen here.
But over here, we have what
could happen if instead,
it's actually X's turn,
because we're one move prior.
There's a bunch of different
moves X could now make, too.
So what is the implication of this?
Well, most humans are not thinking
through tic-tac-toe to this extreme.
And frankly, most of us probably
just don't have the mental capacity
to think about going left and then
right and then left and then right.
Right?
This is not how people play tic-tac-toe.
Like, we're not using that
much memory, so to speak.
But a computer can handle
that, and computers
can play tic-tac-toe optimally.
So if you're beating a
computer at tic-tac-toe, like,
it's not implemented very well.
It's not following this very logical,
deterministic minimax algorithm.
But this is where now AI is
no longer as simple as just
doing what these decision trees say.
In the context of tic-tac-toe,
here's how we might translate this
to code, for instance.
If player is X, for each
possible move, calculate
a score for the board, as
we were doing verbally,
and then choose the move
with the highest score.
Because X's goal is
to maximize its score.
If the player is O, though,
for each possible move,
calculate a score for
the board, and then
choose the move with the lowest score.
So that's a distillation
of that verbal walkthrough
into what CS50 students know now
as code, or at least pseudocode.
But the problem with games, not so
much tic-tac-toe, but other more
sophisticated games is this.
Does anyone want to ballpark
how many possible ways there
are to play tic-tac-toe?
Paper, pencil, two human
children, how many different ways?
How long could you keep them occupied
playing tic-tac-toe in different ways?
If you actually think through,
how big does this tree get,
how many leaves are there on
this decision tree, like how many
different directions, well, if you're
thinking 255,168, you are correct.
And now most of us in our
lifetime have probably not
played tic-tac-toe that many times.
So think about how many games
you've been missing out on.
There are different decisions you
could have been making all these years.
Now, that's a big number, but honestly,
that's not a big number for a computer.
That's a few megabytes of memory
maybe, to keep all of that in mind
and implement that kind of code in
C or Java or C++ or something else.
But other games are
much more complicated.
And the games that you and I
might play as we get older,
they include maybe chess.
And if you think about chess with only
the first four moves, back and forth
four times, so only four moves.
That's not even a very long game.
Anyone want a ballpark
how many different ways
there are to begin a game of chess
with four moves back and forth?
This is evidence as to why
chess is apparently so hard.
288 million ways, which is why
when you are really good at chess,
you are really good at chess.
Because apparently, you
either have an intuition for
or a mind for thinking it would
seem so many more steps ahead
than your opponent.
And don't get us started
on something like Go.
266 quintillion ways to
play Go's first four moves.
So at this point, we just
can't pull out our Mac, our PC,
certainly not our phone, to solve
optimally games like chess and Go,
because we don't have big enough CPUs.
We don't have enough memory.
We don't have enough years in
our lifetimes for the computers
to crunch all of those numbers.
And thus was born a
different form of AI that's
more inspired by finding
patterns more dynamically,
learning from data, as opposed
to being told by humans, here
is the code via which
to solve this problem.
So machine learning is a subset
of artificial intelligence
that tries instead to
get machines to learn
what they should do without being so
coached step by step by step by humans
here.
Reinforcement learning, for instance,
is one such example thereof,
wherein reinforcement
learning, you sort of wait
for the computer or maybe
a robot to maybe just get
better and better and better at things.
And as it does, you reward
it with a reward function.
Give it plus 1 every time
it does something well.
And maybe minus 1.
You punish it any time
it does something poorly.
And if you simply program this AI
or this robot to maximize its score,
never mind minimizing,
maximize its score,
ideally, it should repeat
behaviors that got it plus 1.
It should decrease the
frequency with which it does
bad behaviors that got it negative 1.
And you can reinforce
this kind of learning.
In fact, I have here one demonstration.
Could a student come on
up who does not think
they are particularly coordinated?
If-- OK, wow, you're being
nominated by your friends.
Come on up.
[LAUGHTER]
Their hands went up instantly for you.
OK, what is your name?
AMAKA: My name's Amaka.
DAVID J. MALAN: Amaka, do you want
to introduce yourself to the world?
AMAKA: Hi, my name is Amaka.
I am a first year in Holworthy.
I'm planning to concentrate in CS.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
Nice to see you.
Come on over here.
[APPLAUSE]
So, yes, oh, no, it's sort
of like a game show here.
We have a pan here with what appears
to be something pancake-like.
And we'd like to teach
you how to flip a pancake,
so that when you gesture upward,
the pancake should flip around
as though you cooked the other side.
So we're going to reward you
verbally with plus 1 or minus 1.
Minus 1.
OK, plus 1!
Plus 1, so do more of that.
Minus 1.
Do less of that.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Great, great.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right!
A big round of applause.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
We've been in the habit of handing out
Super Mario Brothers Oreos this year,
so thank you for participating.
[APPLAUSE]
So, this is actually a good
example of an opportunity
for reinforcement learning.
And wonderfully, a researcher has posted
a video that we thought we'd share.
It's about a minute
and a half long, where
you can watch a robot now do exactly
what our wonderful human volunteer here
just attempted as well.
So let me go ahead and
play this on the screen
and give you a sense of what the human
and the robot are doing together.
So their pancake looks
a little similar there.
The human here is going to first
sort of train the robot what
to do by showing it some gestures.
But there's no one right way to do this.
But the human seems to know how
to do it pretty well in this case,
and so it's trying to
give the machine examples
of how to flip a pancake successfully.
But now, this is the very first trial.
OK, look familiar?
You're in good company.
After three trials.
[CLANG]
[PLOP]
OK.
[CLANG]
[PLOP]
OK.
Now 10 tries.
There's the human
picking up the pancake.
After 11 trials--
[CLANG]
[PLOP]
And meanwhile, there's
presumably a human coding this,
in the sense that someone is saying
good job or bad job, plus 1 or minus 1.
20 trials.
Here now we'll see how the computer
knows what it's even doing.
There's just a mapping to some
kind of XYZ coordinate system.
So the robot can quantize
what it is it's doing.
Nice!
To do more of one
thing, less of another.
And you're just seeing a
visualization in the background
of those digitized movements.
And so now, after 50 some odd trials,
the robot, too, has got it spot on.
And it should be able to
repeat this again and again
and again, in order to
keep flipping this pancake.
So our human volunteer wonderfully
took you even fewer trials.
But this is an example
then, to be clear,
of what we'd call
reinforcement learning,
whereby you're reinforcing a behavior
you want or negatively reinforcing.
That is, punishing a
behavior that you don't.
Here's another example
that brings us back
into the realm of games a little
bit, but in a very abstract way.
If we were playing a game
like The Floor Is Lava,
where you're only supposed to step
certain places so that you don't
fall straight in the lava pit or
something like that and lose a point
or lose a life, each of these
squares might represent a position.
This yellow dot might represent the
human player that can go up, down,
left or right within this world.
I'm revealing to the whole
audience where the lava pits are.
But the goal for this yellow
dot is to get to green.
But the yellow dot, as in any good
game, does not have this bird's eye view
and knows from the get-go
exactly where to go.
It's going to have to
try some trial and error.
But if we, the programmers,
maybe reinforce good behavior
or punish bad behavior, we
can teach this yellow dot,
without giving it step
by step, up, down,
left, right instructions,
what behaviors to repeat
and what behaviors not to repeat.
So, for instance, suppose
the robot moves right.
Ah, that was bad.
You fell in the lava already, so
we'll use a bit of computer memory
to draw a thicker red line there.
Don't do that again.
So, negative 1, so to speak.
Maybe the yellow dot moves up next time.
We can reward that behavior
by not drawing any walls
and allowing it to go again.
It's making pretty good progress,
but, oh, darn it, it took a right turn
and now fell into the lava.
But let's use a bit more
of the computer's memory
and keep track of the, OK,
do not do that thing anymore.
Maybe the next time the
human dot goes this way.
Oh, we want to punish
that behavior, so we'll
remember as much with that red line.
But now we're starting to make progress
until, oh, now we hit this one.
And eventually, even though the
yellow dot, much like our human,
much like our pancake flipping robot
had to try again and again and again,
after enough trials, it's going to start
to realize what behaviors it should
repeat and which ones it shouldn't.
And so in this case, maybe it finally
makes its way up to the green dot.
And just to recap, once
it finds that path,
now it can remember it forever as
with these green thicker lines.
Any time you want to leave this
map, any time you get really good
at the Nintendo game, you follow
that same path again and again,
so you don't fall into the lava.
But an astute human observer might
realize that, yes, this is correct.
It's getting out of this so-called maze.
But what is suboptimal or
bad about this solution?
Sure.
AUDIENCE: It's taking
a really long time.
It's not the most
efficient way to get there.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
It's taking a really long time.
An inefficient way to get
there, because I dare say,
if we just tried a
different path occasionally,
maybe we could get lucky
and get to the exit quicker.
And maybe that means we get a higher
score or we get rewarded even more.
So within a lot of artificial
intelligence algorithms,
there's this idea of
exploring versus exploiting,
whereby you should occasionally, yes,
exploit the knowledge you already have.
And in fact, frequently
exploit that knowledge.
But occasionally you know
what you should probably do,
is explore just a little bit.
Take a left instead of a right and
see if it leads you to the solution
even more quickly.
And you might find a
better and better solution.
So here mathematically is
how we might think of this.
10% of the time we might say that
epsilon, just some variable, sort
of a sprinkling of salt into
the algorithm here, epsilon
will be like 10% of the time.
So if my robot or my player picks a
random number that's less than 10%,
that's going to make a random move.
Go left instead of right, even
if you really typically go right.
Otherwise, guys make the
move with the highest value,
as we've learned over time.
And what the robot might learn
then, is that we could actually
go via this path, which gets
us to the output faster.
We get a higher score, we do it
in less time, it's a win-win.
Frankly, this really resonates
with me, because I've
been in the habit, as maybe some of you
are, when you go to a restaurant maybe
that you really like, you
find a dish you really like--
--I will never again know what
other dishes that restaurant
offers, because I'm locally optimally
happy with the dish I've chosen.
And I will never know if there's an
even better dish at that restaurant
unless again, I sort of sprinkle
a little bit of epsilon,
a little bit of randomness into
my game playing, my dining out.
The catch, of course, though,
is that I might be punished.
I might, therefore, be less happy if
I pick something and I don't like it.
So there's this tension between
exploring and exploiting.
But in general in computer
science, and especially in AI,
adding a little bit of
randomness, especially over time,
can, in fact, yield better
and better outcomes.
But now there's this notion
all the more of deep learning,
whereby you're trying to
infer, to detect patterns,
figure out how to solve problems,
even if the AI has never
seen those problems before, and even
if there's no human there to reinforce
positive or negatively behavior.
Maybe it's just too complex
of a problem for a human
to stand alongside the robot
and say, good or bad job.
So with deep learning, they're
actually very much related
to what you might know as neural
networks, inspired by human physiology,
whereby inside of our brains
and elsewhere in our body,
there's lots of these
neurons here that can
send electrical signals
to make movements
happen from brain to extremities.
You might have two of
these via which signals can
be transmitted over a larger distance.
And so computer scientists for
some time have drawn inspiration
from these neurons to create in
software, what we call neural networks.
Whereby, there's inputs
to these networks
and there's outputs from these
networks that represents inputs
to problems and solutions thereto.
So let me abstract away the
more biological diagrams
with just circles that represent
nodes, or neurons, in this case.
This we would call in CS50, the input.
This is what we would call the output.
But this is a very simplistic,
a very simple neural network.
This might be more common,
whereby the network, the AI
takes two inputs to a problem and
tries to give you one solution.
Well, let's make this more real.
For instance, suppose that at the--
suppose that just for the sake of
discussion, here is like a grid
that you might see in math class, with
a y-axis and an x-axis, vertically
and horizontally respectively.
Suppose there's a couple of
blue and red dots in that world.
And suppose that our
goal, computationally,
is to predict whether a dot is
going to be blue or red, based
on its position within
that coordinate system.
And maybe this represents
some real world notion.
Maybe it's something like rain
that we're trying to predict.
But we're doing it more
simply with colors right now.
So here's my y-axis, here's
my x-axis, and effectively,
my neural network you can
think of conceptually as this.
It's some kind of
implementation of software
where there's two inputs to the problem.
Give me an x, give me a y value.
And this neural network will output
red or blue as its prediction.
Well, how does it know whether
to predict red or blue,
especially if no human has
painstakingly written code
to say when you see a dot
here, conclude that it's red.
When you see a dot here,
conclude that it's blue.
How can an AI just learn
dynamically to solve problems?
Well, what might be a
reasonable heuristic here?
Honestly, this is probably a first
approximation that's pretty good.
If anything's to the left of
that line, let the neural network
conclude that it's going to be blue.
And if it's to the
right of the line, let
it conclude that it's going to be red.
Until such time as there's
more training data,
more real world data that gets
us to rethink our assumptions.
So for instance, if
there's a third dot there,
uh-oh, clearly a straight
line is not sufficient.
So maybe it's more of a diagonal line
that splits the blue from the red world
here.
Meanwhile, here's even more dots.
And it's actually getting harder now.
Like, this line is still pretty good.
Most of the blue is up here.
Most of the red is down here.
And this is why, if we fast forward to
today, you know, AI is often very good,
but not perfect at solving problems.
But what is it we're looking at here,
and what is this neural network really
trying to figure out?
Well, again, at the risk of taking
some fun out of red and blue dots,
you can think of this neural network
as indeed having these neurons, which
represent inputs here and outputs here.
And then what's happening
inside of the computer's memory,
is that it's trying to figure out
what the weight of this arrow or edge
should be.
What the weight of this
arrow or edge should be.
And maybe there's
another variable there,
like plus or minus C that
just tweaks the prediction.
So x and y are literally going
to be numbers in this scenario.
And the output of this neural network
ideally is just true or false.
Is it red or blue?
So it's sort of a binary state,
as we discuss a lot in CS50.
So here too, to take the fun
out of the pretty picture,
it's really just like a
high school math function.
What the neural network in this
example is trying to figure out,
is what formula of the
form ax plus by plus c
is going to be arbitrarily
greater than 0?
And if so, let's conclude
that the dot is red
if you get back a positive
result. If you don't, let's
conclude that the dot is
going to be blue instead.
So really what you're
trying to do, is figure out
dynamically what numbers
do we have to tweak,
these parameters inside
of the neural network
that just give us the answer we
want based on all of this data?
More generally though, this would be
really representative of deep learning.
It's not as simple as
input, input, output.
There's actually a lot of
these nodes, these neurons.
There's a lot of these edges.
There's a lot of numbers
and math are going on that,
frankly, even the computer scientists
using these neural networks
don't necessarily know what
they even mean or represent.
It just happens to be that when
you crunch the numbers with all
of these parameters in place,
you get the answer that you want,
at least most of the time.
So that's essentially the
intuition behind that.
And you can apply it to very real
world, if mundane applications.
Given today's humidity, given
today's pressure, yes or no,
should there be rainfall?
And maybe there is some
mathematical function
that based on years of
training data, we can
infer what that prediction should be.
Another one.
Given this amount of
advertising in this month,
what should our sales be for that year?
Should they be up, or
should they be down?
Sorry, for that particular month.
So real world problems map readily
when you can break them down
into inputs and a binary output
often, or some kind of output
where you want the thing to
figure out based on past data what
its prediction should be.
So that brings us back to generative
artificial intelligence, which
isn't just about solving problems, but
really generating literally images,
texts, even videos, that
again, increasingly resemble
what we humans might
otherwise output ourselves.
And within the world of generative
artificial intelligence,
do we have, of course, these
same images that we saw before,
the same text that we saw before,
and more generally, things
like ChatGPT, which are really examples
of what we now call large language
models.
These sort of massive
neural networks that
have so many inputs and so
many neurons implemented
in software, that essentially
represent all of the patterns
that the software has discovered by
being fed massive amounts of input.
Think of it as like the entire
textual content of the internet.
Think of it as the entire
content of courses like CS50
that may very well be out
there on the internet.
And even though these AIs,
these large language models
haven't been told how to
behave, they're really
inferring from all of
these examples, for better
or for worse, how to make predictions.
So here, for instance, from
2017, just a few years back,
is a seminal paper from Google
that introduced what we now
know as a transformer architecture.
And this introduced this idea
of attention values, whereby
they propose that given an English
sentence, for instance, or really
any human sentence, you try to assign
numbers, not unlike our past exercises,
to each of the words, each of the
inputs that speaks to its relationship
with other words.
So if there's a high relationship
between two words in a sentence,
they would have high attention values.
And if maybe it's a preposition or
an article, like the or the like,
maybe those attention values are lower.
And by encoding the
world in that way, do
we begin to detect patterns that
allow us to predict things like words,
that is, generate text.
So for instance, up until a few
years ago, completing this sentence
was actually pretty
hard for a lot of AI.
So for instance here, Massachusetts
is a state in the New England region
of the Northeastern United States.
It borders on the Atlantic
Ocean to the east.
The state's capital is dot, dot, dot.
Now, you should think that this
is relatively straightforward.
It's like just handing you
a softball type question.
But historically within the
world of AI, this word, state,
was so relatively far
away from the proper noun
that it's actually referring
back to, that we just
didn't have computational models
that took in that holistic picture,
that frankly, we humans
are much better at.
If you would ask this question
a little more quickly,
a little more immediately, you
might have gotten a better response.
But this is, daresay, why
chatbots in the past been
so bad in the form of
customer service and the like,
because they're not really
taking all of the context into
account that we humans might
be inclined to provide.
What's going on underneath the hood?
Without escalating things too quickly,
what an artificial intelligence
nowadays, these large
language models might do,
is break down the user's
input, your input into ChatGPT
into the individual words.
We might then encode, we might then take
into account the order of those words.
Massachusetts is first, is is last.
We might further encode each of
those words using a standard way.
And there's different
algorithms for this,
but you come up with what
are called embeddings.
That is to say, you can
use one of those APIs
I talked about earlier, or even
software running on your own computers,
to come up with a
mathematical representation
of the word, Massachusetts.
And Rongxin kindly did
this for us last night.
This is the 1,536 floating
point values that OpenAI uses
to represent the word, Massachusetts.
And this is to say, and
you should not understand
anything you are looking
at on the screen, nor do I,
but this is now a
mathematical representation
of the input that can
be compared against
the mathematical
representations of other inputs
in order to find proximity semantically.
Words that somehow have relationships
or correlations with each other
that helps the AI
ultimately predict what
should the next word out of
its mouth be, so to speak.
So in a case like,
these values represent--
these lines represent all
of those attention values.
And thicker lines means
there's more attention given
from one word to another.
Thinner lines mean the opposite.
And those inputs are ultimately
fed into a large neural network,
where you have inputs on the
left, outputs on the right.
And in this particular
case, the hope is to get out
a single word, which is the capital
of Boston itself, whereby somehow,
the neural network and the humans
behind it at OpenAI, Microsoft, Google,
or elsewhere, have sort of crunched
so many numbers by training
these models on so much data, that it
figured out what all of those weights
are, what the biases are, so
as to influence mathematically
the output therefrom.
So that is all underneath
the hood of what students now
perceive as this adorable rubber duck.
But underneath it all is certainly
a lot of domain knowledge.
And CS50, by nature of being
OpenCourseWare for the past many years,
CS50 is fortunate to actually
be part of the model,
as might be any other content
that's freely available online.
And so that certainly
helps benefit the answers
when it comes to asking
CS50 specific questions.
That said, it's not perfect.
And you might have heard
of what are currently
called hallucinations, where ChatGPT
and similar tools just make stuff up.
And it sounds very confident.
And you can sometimes
call on it, whereby
you can say, no, that's not right.
And it will playfully apologize
and say, oh, I'm sorry.
But it made up some statement,
because it was probabilistically
something that could be said,
even if it's just not correct.
Now, allow me to propose
that this kind of problem
is going to get less and less frequent.
And so as the models evolve
and our techniques evolve,
this will be less of an issue.
But I thought it would
be fun to end on a note
that a former colleague shared
just the other day, which
was this old poem by Shel
Silverstein, another something
from our past childhood perhaps.
And this was from 1981, a poem called
"Homework Machine," which is perhaps
foretold where we are now in 2023.
"The homework machine, oh, the homework
machine, most perfect contraption
that's ever been seen.
Just put in your homework, then
drop in a dime, snap on the switch,
and in ten seconds time, your homework
comes out quick and clean as can be.
Here it is, 9 plus 4,
and the answer is 3.
3?
Oh, me.
I guess it's not as perfect
as I thought it would be."
So, quite foretelling, sure.
[APPLAUSE]
Quite foretelling, indeed.
Though, if for all this and more,
the family members in the audience
are welcome to take CS50
yourself online at cs50edx.org.
For all of today and
so much more, allow me
to thank Brian, Rongxin, Sophie, Andrew,
Patrick, Charlie, CS50's whole team.
If you are a family member here
headed to lunch with CS50's team,
please look for Cameron holding
a rubber duck above her head.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
This was CS50.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]